"How Much Do Doctors Know About Nutrition?"
Humanity's diet is the single
leading cause of death,
exacting an even greater
health burden than smoking.
This makes sense
since we are what we eat.
Literally, physically.
If we continue to rebuild
our body every day
with shoddy materials,
it's no wonder
we run into trouble.
For example, not eating enough
fruits and vegetables
is blamed for millions
of deaths every year.
We should eat fruits
and vegetables
as if our lives depended on it,
because in a way,
it appears they do.
Most Americans may be suffering
from diet-related diseases,
yet most are not being educated
about nutrition
from their doctors.
Maybe that's
actually a good thing
given how little doctors
tend to know about nutrition?
Physicians are typically seen
as trustworthy sources
of nutrition
by the general public,
but in a head-to-head test
of nutrition knowledge,
doctors versus patients,
though physicians
should be more knowledgeable
about nutrition
than their patients,
these results suggest that
this is not necessarily true.
And we all know how little
the general public knows
about nutrition.
The American diet is
the number one cause of death
in the United States,
yet doctors average
less than 20 hours
of nutrition training
and that's mostly
like, you know,
biochemistry of vitamins.
The amount of clinical
nutrition training they may get
is less than five hours.
Take cardiology, for example.
Dr. Ornish's landmark
lifestyle heart trial
asked the question:
"Can lifestyle changes reverse
coronary artery disease?"
And the answer
was a resounding yes.
If just that tidbit alone
were understood
and internalized by internists,
think how many lives
could be saved
from our leading cause
of death and disability,
yet 90 percent
of surveyed cardiologists
reported receiving little
or no nutrition education
during their
cardiology training.
There appears to be
insufficient nutrition training
in medical training
across the board,
a global deficiency.
The low hanging fruit
in medicine
remains on the vine.
And for those doctors who say
they don't have time,
physicians don't need to do
their own diet counseling
any more than
they need to perform
their own x-rays
or blood draws.
But they must
recognize the role
nutrition plays in disease,
communicate it clearly
to patients,
and refer the patient
appropriately.
The diet that Dr. Ornish used
to help reverse
the progression
of heart disease
was whole-food,
plant-based nutrition,
a diet primarily,
but not exclusively,
composed of fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and legumes.
Why isn't there
more widespread acknowledgement
of the power of plants
in the medical community?
One potential reason
is that the science
has yet to make its way
into the teaching materials.
Yes, Dr. Ornish made
this discovery decades ago,
but, sometimes,
it can take decades
for medical practice
to catch up,
even when millions of lives
are at stake.
Nowadays,
it would be unthinkable
not to address
patients' smoking,
because it's just been
incorporated
into the standard of care.
The evidence on nutrition has
yet to be similarly lionized,
but "[t]his should not prevent
thoughtful
and caring clinicians
from applying
safe and effective
nutritional interventions
that are not
'ahead of the evidence'
but only ahead
of the [published] guidelines."
Ignorance of nutrition
is no longer defensible.
There are a growing number
of resources
for those who missed out
in med school.
Doctors can get board certified
in lifestyle medicine.
There are some great websites
out there.
Like PCRM's "Nutrition Guide
for Clinicians."
More great websites.
Yes, it would be nice
not to be a hypocrite
and eat more
healthfully yourself
rather than just learning
about healthier diets,
but that shouldn't stop anyone
from recommending it,
if only because it is
the only diet
that has ever been shown
to reverse the progression
of the number one killer
of men and women,
so people should not be denied
such knowledge.
Now, look, it's their body,
their choice.
Just like many smokers
will continue to smoke,
many will continue to eat junk,
but this should not prevent
clinicians from advising
smoking cessation
and a healthier diet.
Patients have the right
to be told the truth.
Not mentioning
this powerful dietary tool
is an act of withholding
crucial information
necessary
for fully informed consent.
Unfortunately,
out of ignorance,
what many doctors are telling
their patients to eat
may be killing them.
Some doctors used to smoke
with their patients.
In fact, most doctors
themselves smoked,
just like most doctors today
continue to eat foods
that are contributing
to our epidemics
in dietary disease.
Until doctors are taught more
about nutrition,
their advising people
about their diet
could be considered a form
of physician-assisted suicide.